A. D. Bache Collection 1833-1873 Mss.B.B123
American Philosophical Society
A. D. Bache Collection
1833-1873
Mss.B.B123
American Philosophical Society
0.25 Linear feet
Alexander Dallas Bache (1806-1867) was an important scientific reformer during the early nineteenth century. From his position as superintendent of the United States Coast Survey, and through leadership roles in the scientific institutions of the time, Bache helped bring American science into alignment with the professional nature of its European counterparts. In addition, Bache fostered the reform of public education in America. The Alexander Dallas Bache Collection consists of 91 letters written primarily by Bache. In most cases, these are brief notes replying to letters that are not part of the collection. The majority of items relate to Bache's work as superintendent of the U.S. Coast Survey, including letters of recommendation and introduction, and there is minor correspondence regarding the National Academy of Sciences, scientific matters, his travels in Europe, or personal matters. Of particular interest is the letter from Louis Agassiz in 1856 expressing his view of what the natural history museum of the future should be.
Agassiz, Louis, 1807-1873
Babbage, Charles, 1791-1871
Bache, A.D., (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867
Barnes, H. B. (Henry Broughton)
Bond, W. C. (William Cranch), 1789-1859
Brewster, David, Sir, 1781-1868
Chambers, Robert, 1802-1871
Cheney, T. Apoleon (Theseus Apoleon), 1830-1878
Combe, George, 1788-1858
Cooper, Peter, 1791-1883
Dickins, Asbury, 1780-1861
Fessenden, W. P. (William Pitt), 1806-1869
Hale, Charles, 1831-1882
Hilgard, Julius Erasmus, 1825-1891
King, Horatio, 1811-1897
Lee, Samuel Phillips, 1812-1897
Mitchell, Maria, 1818-1889
Paine, [Robert Treat], 1803-1885.
Potter, Alonzo, 1800-1865
Quetelet, Adolphe, 1796-1874
Redfield, W. C. (William C.), 1789-1857
Ruggles, Samuel B., (Samuel Bulkley), 1800-1881
Schofield, John McAllister, 1831-1906
Schumacher, Heinrich Christian, 1780-1850.
Seward, William Henry, 1801-1872
Sparks, Jared, 1789-1866
Spencer, Charles Achilles, 1813-1881
Stevenson, Alan, 1807-1865
Stevenson, David, 1815-1886
Stevenson, Robert, 1772-1850
Tilghman, Tench, 1810-1874
Toucey, Isaac, 1792-1869
Upsher, Able Percey
Vroom, Peter Dumont, 1791-1873
Bibliography
The Library holds over 50 publications of Alexander Dallas Bache, consisting of technical pamphlets and addressess. In addition, there are about 57 titles concerning Bache, primarily journal articles. A complete listing of these works can be found through the Library's OPAC, VOLE.
Naval History Note
The Bache Papers contain at least one item which may be of interest to naval historians:
Bache, Alexander Dallas. Letter to Isaac Toucey. 1859 March 21. Recommends George C. Schaeffer to post at the U.S. Naval Academy. 2 pages.
Early American History Note
This collection consists of a wide-range of general correspondence to and from Alexander Dallas Bache from 1833-1865. The correspondence includes letters to many prominent scientists, such as Louis Agassiz, Maria Mitchell, and Charles Babbage. The content reflects the wide range of Bache’s scientific activity and his extensive contacts. Topics range from cartography to lighthouses to education reform to phrenology.
The bulk of this collection is from 1843-1864, after Bache had taken charge of the Coast Survey and made it the center for federal support of the sciences. Some of the incoming letters contain reports from field work Bache and the U.S. Coast Survey supported. Others are personal in nature. Most letters from Bache are either acknowledgements or letters of introduction. The letters from Maria Mitchell, Charles Babbage, and Louis Aggasiz are notably longer than most letters and are a mix of pleasantries and scientific discussion. One of the longer Aggasiz letters includes his views on natural history museums and their future.
Alexander Dallas Bache was a leading scientist and intellectual in the nineteenth century. He was most prominently Superintendent of the U.S. Coast Survey. Bache used this position to establish better scientific practices in antebellum America and to professionalize the scientific community in the United States. Bache was born into a very prominent family. His great-grandfather was Benjamin Franklin, his grandfather was Alexander James Dallas, Secretary of the Treasury under James Madison, and his uncle George Dallas was James K. Polk’s Vice President. He received his education at West Point, finishing first in his class at age nineteen.
After military service, he accepted a position as a professor of natural philosophy and chemistry at the University of Pennsylvania in 1828. Bache quickly became a leading figure at both the American Philosophical Society and Franklin Institute. He also served as the first president of Girard College. After a trip abroad to study European educational practices, Bache became a leading advocate for educational reform and professionalizing scientific study in America, all of which he modeled off of what he saw in Europe.
After his return to the U.S., Bache sought and received a number of prominent appointments in federal bureaucracies, most notably as head of the U.S. Coast Survey, and served on boards of national institutions, such as the American Association for the Advancement of Science and the Smithsonian Institution. Bache wanted the Coast Survey to serve as a bureaucratic institution dedicated to supporting high quality and rigorous scientific inquiry that would raise the standards and standing of American science. Through his efforts, he successfully made the Coast Survey the single largest employer of scientists in America, and in turn, he was able to establish scientific work as a legitimate professional field, not a playground for wealthy dilettantes. As one of the – if not the – most powerful scientists in America, Bache played a central role in establishing scientific procedures, practices, and standards in antebellum America.
Related Archival Materials note
Additional correspondence with Alexander Dallas Bache can be found in the following collections at the APS: Joseph Winlock Letterbook (B W721), Joseph Henry Letters (B H39p), John K. Kane Papers (B K13), Robert Hare Papers (B H22), Robert M. Patterson Papers (B P274), John L. LeConte Papers (B L493), J. Peter Lesley Papers (B L56), and John Fries Frazer Papers (B F865).
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Acquired from various sources between 1941 and 1983.
Scope and Contents note
The Alexander Dallas Bache Collection consists of 91 letters written primarily by Bache. In most cases, these are brief notes replying to letters that are not part of the collection. The majority of items relate to Bache's work as superintendent of the U.S. Coast Survey, including letters of recommendation and introduction, and there is minor correspondence regarding the National Academy of Sciences, scientific matters, his travels in Europe, or personal matters. Of particular interest is the letter from Louis Agassiz in 1856 expressing his view of what the natural history museum of the future should be.
Biographical/Historical note
Alexander Dallas Bache (1806-1867) was an important scientific reformer during the early nineteenth century. From his position as superintendent of the United States Coast Survey, and through leadership roles in the scientific institutions of the time, Bache helped bring American science into alignment with the professional nature of its European counterpart. In addition, Bache fostered the reform of public education in America.
On July 19, 1806 Alexander Dallas Bache was born into one of Philadelphia's elite families. The son of Richard Bache and Sophia Dallas, he was Benjamin Franklin's great-grandson, nephew to George Dallas (vice president under James K. Polk), and grandson to Alexander James Dallas (secretary of the treasury under James Madison). In 1821, Bache was admitted to the United States Military Academy at the age of 15, graduating first in his class four years later. He remained at the Academy for an additional two years to teach mathematics and natural history. While serving as a lieutenant in the Army Corps of Engineers, working on the construction of Fort Adams in Newport, R.I., he met Nancy Clarke Fowler whom he would later marry.
Bache left the Army in 1828 to begin an academic career, accepting an appointment as professor of natural philosophy and chemistry at the University of Pennsylvania. Although his scientific interests were broad, he had a particular interest in geophyscial research. While in Philadelphia, he constructed a magnetic observatory, and made extensive research into terrestrial magnetism, and during the 1830s he began to be recognized as a leading figure in the city's scientific community. Bache was an active member of the American Philosphical Society and the Franklin Institute, seeking to raise the professional standards of both institutions and urging them to place a stronger emphasis on original research. While at the Franklin Institute from 1830-1835, Bache led a Federally-funded investigation into steam-boiler explosions, the government's first use of technical experts to examine a matter involving public policy.
In 1836 Bache became interested in educational reform when he was asked to help organize the curriculum at Girard College, of which he later served as president. Bache spent two years in Europe visiting over 250 educational institutions. The result of his visit was a 600 page study, Report on Education in Europe, to the Trustees of the Girard College for Orphans published in 1839. Although Bache was unable to apply the report at Girard College because of its delayed opening, it proved useful in overhauling the curriculum of Philadelphia's Central High School, where he was superintendent from 1839-1842, and was widely influential among American educational reformers, helping to introduce the Prussian educational model to the United States.
After meeting many of the leading savants during a European tour, including Alexander von Humboldt, Francois Arago, and Karl Friedrich Gauss, Bache became convinced of the need to professionalize American science. His opportunity to make an impact came in 1843 with the death of Ferdinand Hassler, superindendent of the U.S. Coast Survey. In the years before the Civil War, the Coast Survey supported more scientists then any other institution in the country, and Bache and his colleagues saw the Survey as a means of gaining federal patronage for science. After a campaign by his friends and colleagues, Bache was named as Hassler's replacement. Over the next two decades Bache transformed the Coast Survey into one of the nation's leading scientific institutions, becoming an important patron of science himself in the process. Bache was not just an administrator, but remained personally involved in field work.
Bache also led the reform of American science through his leadership of an elite group known as the "Lazzaroni" or scientific beggars. The goal of the Lazzaroni was to ensure that the nation's leading scientists kept control of the nation's scientific institutions, and they were instrumental in reforming the American Association for the Advancement of Science (of which Bache was president of in 1850). In his remarkably busy schedule, Bache was a member of the Lighthouse Board (1844-1845), superintendent of the Office of Weights and Measures (1844), and a prominent regent for the Smithsonian Institution, where he convinced fellow Lazzaroni Joseph Henry to become its first secretary. Bache also played a leading role in the creation of the National Academy of Sciences, serving as its first president. When the Americn Civil War broke out, Bache focused the Coast Survey to support the war effort, was vice president of the Sanitary Commision, a consultant to the army and navy on battle plans, a superintended for Philadelphia's defence plans, and a member of the Permanent Commission of the navy in charge of evaluating new weapons. Bache died in Newport, R.I. on February 17, 1867.
Antebellum Politics; Cooper Union; Early National Politics; Education; General Correspondence; Geological Survey of the State of New Jersey; Geology; Girard College; Lighthouses; National Academy of Sciences; Natural history; Official Government Documents and Records; Science and Technology; Scientific Correspondence; United States Coast Survey
- ALS to Alexander Dallas Bache, 1833 August 26; 1p.; Paine, R. T. (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Boston, MA. Regarding legislation in Massachusettes on weights and measures.
- ALS to Peter Dumont Vroom, 1835 March 11; 2pp.; Bache, A.D., (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867 (Box 1)
  Philadelphia, PA. Recommends Prof. Henry D. Rogers as a candidate to head the Geological Survey of the State of New Jersey.
- ALS to Alexander Dallas Bache, 1835 October 19; 2pp.; Sparks, Jared (Box 1)
  Cambridge, MA. Inquires that if Bache can not write on Franklin's papers on electricity perhaps Prof. Hare might be able to. Asks if Bache might be able to write notes on the meteorological Papers. On verso is Bache's reply, agreeing to the suggestion of Hare, and he will look at the other.
- ALS to Alexander Dallas Bache, 1837 January 21; 1p.; Combe, George (Box 1)
  Edinburgh. Recommendation of phrenology to Bache for Girard College.
- ALS to Alexander Dallas Bache, 1837 February 7; 1p.; Stevenson, David (Box 1)
  Note to Bache regarding Stevenson calling on him.
- ALS to Alexander Dallas Bache, 1837 March 30; 4pp.; Chambers, Robert, 1802-1871 (Box 1)
  Edinburgh. Is sending Bache his trunk, and discusses books and other objects he requested. Gives his view of England losing its romantic look.
- ALS to Alexander Dallas Bache, 1837 May 16; 2pp.; Stevenson, Alan (Box 1)
  Fragment of letter.
- ALS to Alexander Dallas Bache, 1837; 2pp.; Stevenson, Robert, 1772-1850 (Box 1)
  Sending letters for two Frenchman. Is sending Dr. Warden's copy of the report.
- ALS to Alexander Dallas Bache, 1838 July 9; 2pp.; Schumacher, Heinrich Christian, 1780-1850. (Box 1)
  Altoona. Regarding the plan of survey for Holstein and Luxembourg. Also the survey of Altona.
- ALS to Charles Coquerel, 1839 June 10; 1p.; Bache, A.D., (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867 (Box 1)
  Philadelphia, PA. Letter of introduction for Professor Lilton of the University of Nashville, TN. Refers to sending a copy of Joseph Henry's next memoir.
- ALS to Charles Coquerel, 1839 October 9; 1p.; Bache, A.D., (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867 (Box 1)
  Philadelphia, PA. Letter of introduction for Rev. William Warner, a teacher, who will be visiting Paris. Refers to Girard College trustees and Joseph Henry.
- ALS to Charles Coquerel, 1841 April 9; 1p.; Bache, A.D., (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867 (Box 1)
  Philadelphia, PA. Letter of introduction for Dr. McMillan, who will be studying in Paris.
- ALS to W. C. Redfield, 1841 June 24; 1p.; Bache, A.D., (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867 (Box 1)
  Philadelphia, PA. Regarding Redfield's paper. Photocopy of original owned by the Rosenbach Foundation.
- ALS to the Secretary of the Board of Inspectors of the County Prison, 1841 June 28; 1p.; Bache, A.D., (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867 (Box 1)
  Invitation to visit Central High School.
- ALS to Able Percey Upshur, 1842 November 29; 3pp.; Bache, A.D., (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867 (Box 1)
  Philadelphia, PA. Letter of recommendation for Solon W. Hale for a position of engineer aboard a U.S. Navy steam vessel. On Verso, additional letters of support for Hale from Robert M. Patterson, John F. Frazer, and St. Memch to Upshur.
- ALS to Alexander Dallas Bache, 1843 March 31; 2pp.; Brewster, Sir David (Box 1)
  St. Leonards College, St. Andrews. Asks Bache if he would introduce Professor Potter (bearer of the note) while he is in Washington.
- ALS to unidentified correspondent, 1843 November 13; 1p.; Bache, A.D., (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867 (Box 1)
  Letter to a "Young Friend" that sleeping on duty should not happen again, and his recommendation on what to do when feeling drowsy.
- ALS to Prof. Norton, 1843 November 23; 1p.; Bache, A.D., (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867 (Box 1)
  Philadelphia, PA. Asks for his support in Bache's attempt to obtain the position of Superintendent of the coast survey.
- ALS to John P. Crozier, 1844 May 27; 1p.; Bache, A.D., (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867 (Box 1)
  Office of Coast Survey, Washington, D.C. Acknowledges receipt of his letter of May 13th. Responds regarding the geodetic latitude of his area, and the publication of maps. (Photocopy of original at Delaware County Institute of Science).
- ALS to. Lt. C. P. Paterson, 1845 November 19; 1p.; Bache, A.D., (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867 (Box 1)
  Washington, D.C. Replies to Paterson's letter, comments on disfavor for a change of plan.
- ALS to. Lt. C. P. Paterson, 1845 November 19; 1p.; Bache, A.D., (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867 (Box 1)
  Washington, D.C. Refers Paterson to H. A. Norris of New York to compare findings.
- ALS to. Lt. C. P. Paterson, 1845 November 21; 1p.; Bache, A.D., (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867 (Box 1)
  Norfolk, VA. Provides instructions regarding the transfer of command from Paterson.
- ALS to. Lt. C. P. Paterson, 1845 November 23; 2pp.; Bache, A.D., (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867 (Box 1)
  Coast Survey Office. Instructions regarding the transfer of ships from the Coast Survey to the Navy.
- LS to C. W. Lawrence, 1846 May 11; 1p.; Bache, A.D., (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867 (Box 1)
  Washington, D.C., Office of Weights and Measures. Regarding the receipt at the Custom House of New York of a standard of measure.
- ALS to Asbury Dickins, 1846 December 10; 1p.; Bache, A.D., (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867 (Box 1)
  Regarding the publication of the annual report of the Coast Survey.
- LS to W. C. Bond, 1847 October 11; 1p.; Bache, A.D., (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867 (Box 1)
  Agamentious near South Berwick, ME. Acknowledges receipt of letter of October 8, and the Annual Report of Chronometric Differences in Longitude between Greenwich and Cambridge.
- ALS to Cyrus D. Homer, 1847 December 7; 1p.; Bache, A.D., (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867 (Box 1)
  Washington, D.C., Coast Survey Office. Letter of recommendation for Cyrus Kelley.
- LS to Leonard Paulding, 1848 May 19; 1p.; Bache, A.D., (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867 (Box 1)
  Coast Survey Office, Washington, D. C. Acknowledges Paulding's reporting for duty.
- ALS to W. C. Bond, 1850 June 6; 1p.; Bache, A.D., (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867 (Box 1)
  Coast Survey Office. Asks Bond to distribute reports.
- ALS to Alexander Dallas Bache, 1851 October 2; 1p.; Mitchell, Maria, 1818-1889 (Box 1)
  Nantucket. Asks that Bache sends the material. Comments on the death of Rives.
- ALS to Alexander Dallas Bache, 1851 October 20; 4pp.; Babbage, Charles, 1791-1871 (Box 1)
  London. Regarding the consecutive numbering of lighthouses.
- ALS to Alexander Dallas Bache, 1851 November 8; 2pp.; Mitchell, Maria, 1818-1889 (Box 1)
  Nantucket. Thanks Bache for his comments, is returning the books she borrowed. States she would like to see the apparatus if ever in Washington. Personal notes.
- LS to Samuel B. Ruggles, 1852 February 25; 1p.; Bache, A.D., (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867 (Box 1)
  Washington, D.C. Regarding the article on the Polytechnic School of France in Bache's Report on Education.
- LS to Hugh Maxwell, 1852 April 14; 1p.; Bache, A.D., (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867 (Box 1)
  Office of Weights and Measures. Instructing him to send a standard measurer to Alexander Vatternare in Paris.
- ALS to Alexander Dallas Bache, 1852 May 24; 1p.; Sparkes, Jared (Box 1)
  Cambridge. Regarding the publication of the Astronomical Journal.
- ALS to Alexander Dallas Bache, 1853 March 4; 3pp.; Potter, Alonzo, 1800-1865 (Box 1)
  Philadelphia, PA. Potter comments on the lack of a reply from Bache, and Potter's plan which has not been well received by the faculty.
- ALS to George C. Schaeffer, 1853 April 2; 1p.; Bache, A.D., (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867 (Box 1)
  Regrets missing him, has left letters.
- ALS. to J. M. Wample, 1853 April 4; 2pp.; Bache, A.D., (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867 (Box 1)
  Wilmington, N.C. Replies to Wample's letter of April 1 to leave the Coast Survey after not being placed in charge of a triangulation party, and Bache's reason for not putting him in charge.
- LS to L. Y. Lyne, 1853 July 21; 1p.; Bache, A.D., (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867 (Box 1)
  Near Leeds Station, Me. Reply to Lyne's request to be detached from the schooner Morris.
- ALS to unidentified correspondent, 1853 September 23; 3pp.; Bache, A.D., (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867 (Box 1)
  Mt. Blue near Phillips, Me. Relates to efforts to establish a national academy of science.
- ALS to Julius E. Hilgard, 1853 October 19; 1p.; Bache, A.D., (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867 (Box 1)
  Mt. Blue. Personal letter.
- ALS to Alexander Dallas Bache, 1853 November 3; 1p.; Agassiz, Louis, 1807-1873 (Box 1)
  Cambridge. Discusses Lyell contacting Hall for information. Comments on Bache's efforts to establish the Academy.
- ALS to J. A. Delanter, 1854 January 20; 3pp.; Bache, A.D., (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867 (Box 1)
  Washington, D.C. Regarding Bishop Peters [?] and the University of Pennsylvania.
- ALS Samuel B. Ruggles, 1854 February 2; 3pp.; Bache, A.D., (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867 (Box 1)
  Washington, D.C.
- ALS to Alexander Dallas Bache, 1854 April 29; 1p.; Agassiz, Louis, 1807-1873 (Box 1)
  Cambridge. Agassiz reply to Bache for not fulfilling an obligation, and wishes to explain why.
- ALS to Wm. C. Bond and Son, 1854 November 6; 1p.; Bache, A.D., (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867 (Box 1)
  Near Camden, ME. Sending Coast Survey Transit No. 8 by steam ship.
- ALS to Edward Meriam, 1855 May 23; 1p.; Bache, A.D., (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867 (Box 1)
  Charleston, S.C. Regarding Walter R. Jones, and Bache's work in Florida.
- LS to [Myron E. Clark] Governor of the State of New York, 1856 June 12; 1p.; Bache, A.D., (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867 (Box 1)
  Washington, D.C., Office of Weights and Measures. Requesting copies of legislation regarding weights and measures in the state of New York.
- ALS to Alexander Dallas Bache, 1856 August 5; 4pp.; Agassiz, Louis, 1807-1873 (Box 1)
  Cambridge. Agassiz's views on what a future natural history museum should be, and how the present ones developed around individual branches of science (such as anatomy, and paleontology).
- ALS to Alexander Dallas Bache, 1856 September 17; 1p.; Cooper, Peter, 1791-1883 (Box 1)
  New York, NY. Relating to the founding of Cooper Union, and Bache's approval of the building plan.
- ALS to Alexander Dallas Bache, 1856 October 30; 2pp.; Potter, Alonzo, 1800-1865 (Box 1)
  Contacting Bache to advise Mrs. Brown on her son entering the Coast Survey rather then the military.
- LS to Marshall S. Wilder, 1857 January 15; 1p.; Bache, A.D., (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867 (Box 1)
  Coast Survey Office, Washington, D.C. Invitation to the U.S. Agricultural Society to visit the Coast Survey office.
- ANS to H. B. Barnes, 1857 February 26; 1p.; Bache, A.D., (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867 (Box 1)
  Note sending an autograph.
- LS to T. Apoleon Cheney, 1858 June 5; 1p.; Bache, A.D., (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867 (Box 1)
  Coast Survey Office. Regarding the forwarding of publications.
- ALS to T. Apoleon Cheney, 1858 July 24; 3pp.; Bache, A.D., (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867 (Box 1)
  Washington, D.C. Regarding funding to the Coast Survey, additions to the coast, and completion of the project.
- LS to Horatio King, 1858 September 30; 1p.; Bache, A.D., (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867 (Box 1)
  Revere House, Boston, MA. Sending copy of Coast Survey report and sketches for 1856 as requested.
- LS to the Committee on the Central High School of Philadelphia, 1858 November 25; 1p.; Bache, A.D., (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867 (Box 1)